PRESENTER: Hello everyone, and
welcome to the content video
for the Graph Data Structure.
OK, so the Graph Data
Structure, there's
some similarities between
the Tree Data Structure
and the Graph Data Structure.
But some key differences.
So a tree, as you can
see in my image here--
a tree has a parent-child
relationship.
And the nodes, or the
data that's stored,
are connected through
these edges from parent
to child, or from
root down to leaf.
So the graph is
similar, but the changes
are a node can have
multiple parents.
And you can think of it
like multiple children.
So really the rule of one
parent to two children
doesn't exist in a graph.
A node can be connected to
other nodes by as many edges
as you want.
There is a concept of successor
and predecessor in graphs.
But really, it can be--
there's no limit.
There's no limit to
the number of nodes
or the number of
edges in a graph.
Graphs are used,
really, all over.
But the common
thing between them
all is that there
needs to be nodes,
or really where the
data pieces are stored.
And then edges, or-- which
can be a physical connection,
a representation of a physical
connection, or a relationship,
including a mathematical
relationship.
But something that connects
the nodes to each other.
As I mentioned, a graph is a
tree with multiple children
and parents.
And consistently,
you'll see the verbiage
that's used when talking about
graphs is vertices and edges.
But vertices are just
nodes-- same things.
And I commonly use the
term nodes and edges,
but vertices, same thing.
So vertices and edges.
But it's a set of those.
So a set of nodes, and then a
set of edges that connect that
nodes in whatever way you want.
Graphs are all over the place.
They represent physical
things, like hardware networks,
and/or logical things,
like this example
of if you want to get a
degree in computer science--
and this one's a little bit
old, but the idea the idea
is the same.
You start here, and then you
go through all these classes,
and eventually you get down to
the bottom right of this graph
where you graduate.
Well, the edges
represent the workflow
and then the classes
represent the nodes.
That's the relationship.
Now, the relationship
matters, obviously,
because you can't take
classes in any order you want.
There's a structure
and an ordering to it.
So the combination of
those nodes and edges
together gives that
relationship, gives those--
gives that structure to
the graph to represent it.
So you start here.
You go through, take
CS1400, 1410, 2420.
And then, as you take
those, it opens up
the possibility of other
classes for you to take.
You still have your prereqs over
here, your gen ed requirements.
And then eventually, once
you've got everything done,
you make it over to
where you graduate.
Another common example.
So this would be
a physical example
that's represented with a
graph, would be bus routes.
So the edges here would
actually be a physical road,
and the nodes here
would also be physical.
They'd be a physical bus stop.
And the relationships,
obviously,
are where can I
go on this route.
So you have to think of it
in terms of the application,
is what nodes can I get to?
I need to go on a bus
to get to another node.
And then, obviously,
it shows you
the edges you're going to
traverse as you go along.
So that's another classic
example of a graph.
Matching algorithm.
So this is a logical
example of a graph.
The nodes here would be
people, and the edges
would represent a relationship
between them, which
could be an employee,
a job, or a dating app,
or website that
would match people.
The nodes would still
be people there.
And then the edges would
be the relationship
you're trying to match
between the people.
So the node here is physical, a
person, and the edge is logical,
a relationship.
Whoop.
There we go.
So some other terms when you're
dealing with graph-- and this
really sets up when we talk
about traversing a graph,
or how to get through
graphs the fastest,
or how to calculate things
efficiently to make decisions
with the data in a graph.
Here's some terminology
and some concepts
we're going to need for those.
So graph, we mentioned, is
a set of vertices and edges
connected with--
or, excuse me, of vertices
and nodes connected by edges.
Commonly, when you see
mathematical representations--
you know, the--
it'll be V and E.
This relationship
of successor-predecessor,
it's similar to a tree
structure of parent-child,
but not necessarily.
Successor and
predecessor, now, more
has to do with the way
you traverse a graph.
So for the example of getting
a computer science degree,
there's an obvious flow there
of successor-predecessor,.
But that not necessarily--
that might not necessarily
be the case in every graph.
It might be a
logical relationship,
where you could go-- a
predecessor could go back
and visit a successor again.
Maybe to try and use that
getting a degree example,
Maybe you have to go back and
take a class for some reason.
That would be like going
back to the successor.
And then degrees.
Degrees are the number
of edges each node has
or each vertex has.
The indegree is the
number of edges coming in,
and the outdegree is the
number of edges going out.
There's another
relationship we need
to cover when
talking about graphs,
is directed versus undirected.
So directed refers to
when an edge has a--
an edge is an arrow.
An edge has a flow to it.
It has a--
It cannot be-- an edge going
from node A to node B does not
necessarily, in
a directed graph,
mean there's an edge back from
B to A. So the direction matters
in a directed graph.
Undirected is there's
no concept of that.
Any edge-- like, for example,
the matching algorithm--
if you're trying to match
people in a dating app,
if they're a match, then that
just means an edge exists.
There's a relationship or
a possible relationship
between these two people,
whereas maybe in a network flow,
or back to the bus
routes-- let me put that
in really quick-- traffic flow.
Traffic flow could
kind of be both.
So a-- traffic could
be an undirected graph
if, for the roads that
are represented by edges,
there's flow to
and from the nodes.
So both-- two-way traffic.
You can go both ways.
However, if there's
a one-way street,
then that would be directed.
You can only go one direction.
So that edge would
have a direction to it.
And then the terminology
is a little bit different.
So indegree for directed graph,
it's indegree and outdegree,
which-- the number of edges
coming in and leaving.
But if it's undirected,
where there's not
the concept of in and out,
it's just called degree--
degree and neighbors--
when talking
about an undirected graph.
OK, so younger than.
So you tell me what kind of
graph is this going to be,
directed or undirected?
Well, one pretty big hint.
You can go look at
the graph right away
and see that it has arrows.
So you know that it's directed.
But they're arrows, though.
It's not directed
because we have arrows.
It's because the
relationship is directed.
So in this example,
it's a younger than.
Point to someone who's
younger than you.
Well, that right
there is you need
to determine the relationship
of who is younger than me.
That brings in a direction.
That person is younger than me.
That person is older than me.
I'm not going to point to them,
but they can point back to me.
That's a directed graph.
So even though
it's not physical,
it's still the relationship
determines it's directed.
OK.
Another example of a graph--
and this is kind of setting up
how you store a graph, what,
what data structure, what
data types, and the structure
of a graph looks like
when you store it.
So here's an example of
someone you want to work with.
You can look at the vertices.
So here, it'll be a set.
Notice the squirrely braces.
Although it's not really a
dictionary, this is kind of--
I'm using-- this slide refers to
the mathematic notation of it,
not necessarily the Python code.
So here's all the edge--
0, 1, 2, 3, 4.
And then the-- excuse me, here's
all the nodes, 0, 1, 2, 3, 4.
And then the edges, notice
they're always in pairs--
0,1; 1,2; 0,3; 3,0; 2,2; 4,3.
So we can go down here and see
all of those edges are directed.
So here's all of the
arrows between the nodes.
And what about this
loop here, 2,2?
Well, we have an
edge from 2 to 2.
So that would be a loop.
That's exactly what
a loop is in a graph,
is when you have one
node, have an edge that
comes back to itself.
And that could
represent something
in the physical
world, like a park
up in the mountains
where a road from a cabin
goes around to see
something beautiful,
and it just comes
back around to itself.
And that's all the road
does, is loop around
so you can see the
beautiful environment.
That could be an example
of a loop inside a graph.
But yeah, there it is.
And, as I mentioned,
this is really commonly
what you're going to use
graphs for in the real world
in your job one day, is graphs
that represent relationships.
The node x likes y, like if it's
a customer and they're shopping,
what's a product
they might like?
x knows how to contact
y in a contact list.
A friend of y, x, wants to work
for y-- like a LinkedIn kind
of scenario there.
x is a child of y.
If you're thinking,
well, I thought
we left child and parent
structures with trees,
well yeah.
But you can just
make a child edge,
and then this edge
represents a child,
and start using those edges.
And then you've,
you've brought back
in the parent-child
relationship.
There's a flight
from x to x to y.
Clubs x and y share common
members, things like that.
So there's countless
examples of relationships.
And when you start
to think about--
you know, that's really
what graphs are used for,
is when you have a system
where the relationships get
complex, a list, a dictionary,
a table, and a database
doesn't quite capture it all.
And you need
something to capture
both the data itself
and the relationship
with other pieces of data.
A graph is perfect for that.
OK.
And I threw some examples.
I put into ChatGPT, "What are
some examples of the real world
of graphs used today?"
Social networks,
heavily, obviously.
The networks that you
participate in in social media
are represented by graphs.
Search engines use-- represent
websites, and hyperlinks,
and the connection between
websites using graphs.
Transportation networks,
we talked about.
Recommendation systems,
like Amazon, connecting user
nodes to items or services
that they would like.
So the relationship there would
be something they would like
or something they'd
like to purchase--
would be the graph and the node
in the edge relationship there.
Obviously, physical
network infrastructure
is a classic example of a graph,
and still heavily used today.
And then knowledge graphs.
Knowledge, if you look
at knowledge-- and again,
a parallel to this would
be how to get a degree.
Well, that has a flow to it.
You need classes that build on
each other to get you to the end
where you have a degree.
Knowledge itself follows
that same pattern.
Before you get
calculus, you need
to learn arithmetic, and
algebra, and geometry.
Knowledge itself kind
of has a flow to it.
The knowledge components have
relationships among themselves.
So using graphs to
represent knowledge
and how knowledge can
be learned by someone--
a graph is a good fit for that.
OK.
And that concludes this
content video of the Graph Data
Structure overview.
Thanks for watching.